בוקר טוב. Boker tov.
Today's דף daf is דף ד. Daf Dalet. We pick up about
eight lines in at the two
dots, חוץ מנחת חוטא ומנחת קנאות. Chutz mi-minchat choteh u-minchat kenaot. So
we just spent some time discussing רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon position that
a שלא לשמו shelo lishmo intent does not create a problem by
מנחה, mincha, at least by many מנחות minchot or whatever, and we
discussed different reasons. Now we get to the next line of the
משנה mishna that says that שלא לשמו shelo lishmo operates by מנחה
mincha the same way it does by animal sacrifices, which is by
most sacrifices, it says it's כשר kosher but it doesn't count for
the owners. And by a מנחה mincha for a חוטא choteh and
standing in the place of a חטאת chatat or the
מנחה mincha for a sin and the מנחה mincha for a סוטה
sotah woman suspected of sinning, there it's like חטאת chatat and that
if it's done שלא לשמו, shelo lishmo, the whole thing is invalid.
So that's what the גמרא gemara picks up with, חוץ מנחת חוטא
ומנחת קנאות. chutz mi-minchat choteh u-minchat kenaot. בשלמא מנחת חוטא חטאת קריה
רחמנא, Bishlama minchat choteh chatat karaya rachmana, so I get a מנחה
mincha of a sinner, it's even called in the
תורה Torah a
חטאת. chatat. לא ישים עליה שמן ולא יתן עליה לבונה כי חטאת
היא, Lo yasim aleha shemen velo yiten aleha levona ki chatat hi,
because it is a חטאת. chatat. Okay, and that's exactly anyway it's
brought also a substitute for a חטאת chatat in one of those
types of קרבנות korbanot where you what you bring can vary based
on your ability to afford it.
אלא מנחת קנאות מנלן, Ella minchat kenaot minalan,
how about a מנחה mincha for about the סוטה, sotah, where do
you know there if it's שלא לשמו shelo lishmo it's invalid? דתני
תנא קמיה דרב נחמן, Detani tanna kamay de-Rav Nachman, as the תנא
tanna taught in the presence of רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, מנחת קנאות
מותרה נדבה. minchat kenaot mosara nidava. So if you have leftover money
designated for a מנחת קנאות, minchat kenaot, you set aside some money
and you didn't need all of it, the extra money goes for
a נדבה, nidava, a free will עולה olah offering. It goes into
that one of those boxes that they had in the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash where people would put various moneys that were used for
this purpose and then when nobody was it was a slow day
at the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, they would draw on those funds
and use them to bring an עולה, olah, an עולת ציבור. olat
tzibbur. Okay, so that's what the תנא tanna taught to רב נחמן.
Rav Nachman. רב נחמן Rav Nachman said to him, אמר ליה שפיר
קאמרת. amar lei shappir kamarta. That makes sense that teaching. מזכרת עוון
כתיב בה, Mazkeret avon kesiv bah, by the מנחה mincha for the
סוטה sotah it says that causes sin to be remembered. ובחטאת כתיב
U-vechatat kesiv and by a normal חטאת, chatat, an animal חטאת, chatat,
it says ואותה נתן לכם לשאת את עוון העדה. v'osah nasan lachem
laseis es avon ha-edah. It has the same word עוון, avon, sin,
iniquity. It's given to you to lift up the sin of the
congregation. מה חטאת מותרה נדבה, Mah chatat mosara nidava,
so it should be linked to a חטאת. chatat. And by חטאת
chatat we say although if you have an animal as a חטאת
chatat and you couldn't bring it for you know there are various
reasons, another one was brought or something of that nature, then the
animal has to die, it's חטאת המתה. chatat ha-meisa. But if you
had money set aside for חטאת chatat and leftover money, we learn
from a פסוק pasuk in the actually about כסף אשם וכסף חטאת
לכהנים יהיו kessef asham ve-kessef chatat la-kohanim yihiyu etc., a פסוק pasuk
in תנ"ך, Tanach, we learn that actually the leftover money of a
חטאת chatat goes for an עולה. olah. So since that's true about
a חטאת, chatat, אף מנחת קנאות מותרה נדבה, af minchat kenaot mosara
nidava, it's true about this מנחת סוטה minchat sotah because the words
עוון עוון avon avon link it. Now once you say that, that
also lets us say this הלכה halacha that שלא לשמו shelo lishmo
invalidates. וכחטאת, U-kechatat,
it should function just like a חטאת chatat once you have that
link. מה חטאת פסולה שלא לשמו, Mah chatat pesula shelo lishmo, the
same way שלא לשמו shelo lishmo invalidates by a חטאת, chatat, so
אף מנחת קנאות פסולה שלא לשמו. af minchat kenaot pesula shelo lishmo.
The same by מנחת קנאות. minchat kenaot. So that's what we learn
from the עוון עוון avon avon that links it to a חטאת.
chatat. So the גמרא gemara says אלא מעתה, ella me'ata, if that's
what you're doing it based on the עוון עוון avon avon to
link it and that says שלא לשמו shelo lishmo is invalid, there's
other things it says עוון avon and I should make
the same sort of application, the same principle הלכה. halacha. What? Well
the obvious always the next candidate after a חטאת, chatat, the most
obvious thing that's similar to a חטאת chatat is an אשם. asham.
אלא מעתה Ella me'ata says the גמרא gemara once you're basing it
on the link of the words
עוון עוון, avon avon, אשם יהא פסול שלא לשמו, asham yehei passul
shelo lishmo, say an אשם asham that's done not with the right
intent is invalid.
דגמר עוון עוון מחטאת degamar avon avon mi-chatat because by אשם asham
it also says עוון. avon. Okay, it says רש"י Rashi quotes the
פסוק, pasuk, what פסוק pasuk by אשם, asham, ולא ידע ואשם ונשא
עוונו. velo yada ve-ashem ve-nasa avono. Okay, so let's say similar, it
says עוון avon by אשם, asham, עוון avon by חטאת chatat and
שלא לשמו shelo lishmo is invalid. So
the גמרא gemara says no, דנין עוון מעוון ואין דנין עוונו מעוון.
donin avon me-avon ve-ein donin avono me-avon. No, by חטאת chatat and
a מנחה mincha and by מנחת קנאות minchat kenaot it says עוון.
avon.
מזכרת עוון, Mazkeret avon, לשאת את עוון העדה. laseis es avon ha-edah.
By an אשם asham it says ונשא עוונו, ve-nasa avono, so it's
not an exact match. So the גמרא gemara says מאי נפקא מינה,
mai nafka mina, so who cares if it's an exact match or
not? It's close enough. והא תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל, ve-ha tanna devei
Rabbi Ishmael, we know you can make a גזירה שוה gezeira shavah
even if the match isn't exact because it's taught in the house
of רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Ishmael, ושב הכהן ובא הכהן. ve-shav ha-kohen u-va
ha-kohen. This is by the... This is by the מצורע. metzora. He
returns and he comes. Two separate פסוקים pesukim and we link the
הלכות halachos of one to the other because they say we're both
referring to the כהן kohen coming back to the house even though
it's not the same word. זו היא שיבה וזו היא ביאה. Zo
hi shiva vezo hi viah. Since it's essentially the same, coming back
to the house, even though they're two really completely different words, we're
allowed to make a גזירה שוה. gezeira shava. So this is what
the גמרא Gemara always quotes when it wants to say a גזירה
שוה gezeira shava doesn't have to be precise. Okay, now sometimes what
the גמרא Gemara will say is, okay, but you'd rather make a
precise link than an imprecise link. Fine, that's if you had to
choose. Should I make the גזירה שוה gezeira shava with A, which
is precise, or B, which is imprecise? But here you don't have
to choose. Just say that חטאת Chatas teaches, the same way חטאת
Chatas teaches to a מנחת קנאות, minchas knaos, it teaches to an
אשם Asham even though it's not exactly a link by an אשם.
Asham. It's not that it links to an אשם Asham more than
it links to a מנחת קנאות. minchas knaos. In addition to linking
to a מנחת קנאות, minchas knaos, and therefore why not tell me
the same thing? ועוד, Vaod, and the גמרא Gemara says and even
if you want to say no, it has to be exact, לגמר
עוונו עוונו ligmar avono avono from עוון דשמיעת הקול. avon deshmias hakol.
It says the word עוונו avono by a חטאת Chatas as well,
exactly by this חטאת Chatas of the varying value קרבן, korban, דכתיב
אם לא יגיד ונשא עוונו. dechshiv im lo yagid venasa avono. Okay,
so if it's based on the link to the word עוונו, avono,
it explains why a מנחת קנאות שלא לשמה minchas knaos shelo lishmah
is invalid, but it doesn't explain why you don't say the same
thing about an אשם. Asham. So the גמרא Gemara says
אלא, ela, says the גמרא, Gemara, fine, כי גמר גזירה שוה למותר
נדבה הוא דגמיר. ki gamar gezeira shava lemosar nedavah hu degamir. So
what you see you have to say is, is that the גזירה
שוה gezeira shava only tells you this הלכה halacha of the extra
moneys that for, you know, the same way extra moneys for a
חטאת Chatas goes for an עולה, olah, extra moneys for a מנחת
קנאות minchas knaos goes to an עולה. olah. And that's it. And
it doesn't tell you this הלכה halacha about שלא לשמה, shelo lishmah
because again, if you said it, you should logically say the same
thing by an אשם. Asham. Now, וכי תימא אין גזירה שוה למחצה?
vechi teima ein gezeira shava lemachetza? So you're going to say, oh
wait, wait, wait, wait, wait, but once you make a גזירה שוה,
gezeira shava, you have to, I don't know why it doesn't say
it by an אשם. Asham. But what I do know is, is
that we
make a
גזירה שוה gezeira shava here by
מנחת קנאות minchas knaos about the leftover funds. And once you have
a גזירה שוה, gezeira shava, you don't make it halfway and that
tells you שלא לשמה shelo lishmah, is invalid. The גמרא Gemara says,
you know what? Even that's not a good argument. Why? Because גלי
רחמנא גבי חטאת ושחט אותה לחטאת. gali rachmana gabei Chatas veshachat osah
lechatas. By a חטאת, Chatas,
the idea that it has to be לשמה, lishmah, that it has
to be שחוטה לשמה, shchuta lishmah, it says, you שחט shachat it
for a חטאת. Chatas. So for a חטאת, Chatas, it has to
be לשמה. lishmah. And the word אותה osah is a very narrowing
word. And what אותה osah tells you is, אותה לשמה כשירה שלא
לשמה פסולה. osah lishmah ksheira shelo lishmah psula. By a חטאת Chatas
is where we say that it has to be שחוטה shchuta for
a חטאת Chatas and if it's not done for the right reason,
it's ממש mamash invalid. Not just it doesn't count for the owner,
but it's ממש mamash invalid. That's true by a חטאת, Chatas, but
by a חטאת Chatas the word אותה osah means this הלכה halacha
is only true by a חטאת. Chatas. אבל כל קדשים בין לשמן
בין שלא לשמן כשרים. Aval kol kodashim bein lishman bein shelo lishman
ksherim. But by all other קדשים, kodashim, the general rule should be
they're okay. So don't tell me for a technical reason if I'm
making a גזירה שוה gezeira shava to מנחת קנאות minchas knaos that
the leftover money goes for an עולה, olah, I have to apply
it across the board. You have a limiting word by a חטאת
Chatas that says אותה, osah, that tells you don't feel you have
to apply this across the board. So bottom line is, while I
understand the attraction that you want to say that a חטאת שלא
לשמה Chatas shelo lishmah is, that a מנחת קנאות minchas knaos שלא
לשמה shelo lishmah is invalid because of the link of עוונו עוונו
avono avono to חטאת, Chatas, which we're already linking for the הלכה
halacha of the extra moneys go to an עולה, olah, nevertheless, says
the גמרא, Gemara, it's not, it's not a valid point. Because then
you should say the same thing about an אשם. Asham. And don't
tell me that once you make a גזירה שוה gezeira shava you
have to make it across the board, you have a limiting word
אותה. osah. So you really haven't explained why by מנחת קנאות minchas
knaos we know this הלכה halacha that שלא לשמה shelo lishmah is
invalid. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this, אלא מנחת חוטא ומנחת קנאות דפסול שלא לשמן מנלן? Ela minchas
choteh uminchas knaos depsul shelo lishman manalan? So here's why. Not because
of that it says by מנחת חוטא חטאת. minchas choteh Chatat. And
not because of a גזירה שוה gezeira shava by מנחת קנאות. minchas
knaos. No. Internal in the פסוקים pesukim themselves by a מנחת חוטא
minchas choteh or מנחת קנאות, minchas knaos, we're going to learn that
שלא לשמה shelo lishmah is invalid. How is that? Because the same
way we know that a חטאת Chatas is invalid. חטאת טעמא מאי?
Chatas taama mai? How do we know a חטאת שלא לשמה Chatas
shelo lishmah is totally invalid? So משום דכתיב בה היא. mishum dechshiv
bah hi. Because the verse says חטאת היא. Chatat hi. And if
you remember going way back to זבחים, Zevachim, the דרשה derasha was
היא לשמה כשירה שלא לשמה פסולה. hi lishmah ksheira shelo lishmah psula.
It has to be only for a חטאת. Chatas. Any sort of
derailing invalidates it. That's the word היא. hi. So if the word
היא hi tells you any derailing invalidates, well guess what? Forget that
we're not going to link it to a חטאת. Chatas. By מנחת
חוטא minchas choteh itself and by מנחת קנאות minchas knaos itself, it
says the word היא. hi. Okay. הכי נמי הכתיב בהו היא. hachi
nami haksiv behu hee. Why? Because it says, we quoted the פסוק
pasuk before, it says לא ישים עליה שמן ולא יתן עליה לבונה
כי חטאת היא. lo yasim aleha shemen v'lo yiten aleha levona ki
chatat hee. Okay. And the פסוק'ס pasuk's that's by a מנחת חוטא
minchas chotei and by מנחת קנאות minchas knaos it says כי מנחת
קנאות היא. ki minchas knaos hee. So since it has the word
היא, hee, she is, it is, and so on, that tells you
any derailing invalidates, not because it's linked to a חטאת. chatas. Just
the word היא hee tells you that. Okay, says the גמרא, Gemara,
but guess what our question is going to be. אשם נמי הוא
דכתיב הא כתיב בהו היא. asham nami hu d'chsiv ha ksiv behu
hee. By an אשם asham it also says אשם הוא אשם אשם
לה'. asham hu asham asham l'Hashem.
So it has the same word by an אשם. asham. So same
thing by an אשם asham that any derailing invalidates? So the גמרא
Gemara says no. ההוא הוא, hahu hu, that הוא hu by an
אשם, asham, אשם הוא, asham hu, ואחר הקטרת אימורים הוא דכתיב. v'achar
haktaras emurim hu d'chsiv. That's read, written in the תורה Torah after
it says that you offer up all of the entrails. Okay? Because
it says והקטיר אותם הכהן המזבחה אשה לה' אשם הוא. v'hiktir osam
hakohen hamizbeacha isheh l'Hashem asham hu. Offer up the entrails on the
altar, it is an אשם. asham. So the word הוא, hu, it,
which normally we say means if you derail it, it's invalid, cannot
be what it means by an אשם. asham. Why? Because by an
אשם, asham, it said after the entrails are put on the altar.
And even if you didn't do the entrails, it's כשר. kasher. So
the emphasizing that it has to be done for the right reason
and the wrong reason invalidates that we normally read into the word
הוא hu cannot be what it's saying by an אשם, asham, because
once you get to that stage of the ritual by the אשם,
asham, you can't invalidate it anyway. Okay? ודכתיב
דתניא, u'dchsiv d'tanya, like we've done in the ברייתא, braita, אבל אשם
לא נאמר בו הוא אלא לאחר הקטרת אימורים. aval asham lo ne'emar
bo hu ela l'achar haktaras emurim. It only says it after the
אימורים emurim are offered up on the altar. והוא עצמו שלא הוקטרו
אימוריו כשר. v'hu atzmo shelo huktru imurav kasher. And even if you
didn't do the אימורים emurim it would be כשר, kasher, so doing
the אימורים emurim wrong can't invalidate. So the היא hee that it
says by a חטאת, chatas, a
מנחת חוטא, minchas chotei, a מנחת קנאות, minchas knaos, it says it
at an early stage. And therefore we can say what that היא
hee is telling you is if you derail it at this early
stage, you invalidate. But that can't be what the הוא hu by
an אשם asham is telling you because there it's written in the
תורה Torah at a later stage. Okay, so what is that הוא
hu by an אשם asham telling you? So the גמרא Gemara says
והוא למה לי? v'hu lama li? So what is that הוא hu
telling you by an
אשם? asham?
למה לי? lama li? לכדרב הונא אמר רב, l'chiderav huna amar rav,
like רב הונא אמר רב, Rav Huna Amar Rav, as he says,
אשם שניתק לרעייה
ושחטו סתם כשר לשם עולה. asham shenitak l'raaya u'shchato stam kasher l'shem
ola. So if you know that if you have an אשם asham
that for some reason can't be brought, it got lost, you brought
another one, and something of that nature. The הלכה halacha is, is
that it gets transferred to an עולה. ola. How does it get
transferred to an עולה? ola? You wait for it to get a
blemish. Once it gets a blemish, you transfer, you redeem it, you
transfer the value to money and use the money to bring an
עולה. ola. Now, let's say this אשם, asham, so you were waiting
for it to get a blemish. So what do you do? You
gave it to a shepherd. And the shepherd was going to graze
it and he was going to report to you when it got
a blemish and then you could know you could move on to
the next stage. And then after that stage, after it was given
for grazing, you שחט'ד shechted it in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
without any particular intent, not intending as an אשם. asham. If you
intended as an אשם asham it would be invalid. But you did
it סתם, stam, you just the sheep came to the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash and you שחט'ד shechted it. And the הלכה halacha is
at that stage it counts as an עולה. ola. Since it's on
the path to being an עולה, ola, once it gets a blemish
it'll be redeemed and the money will go to an עולה. ola.
And therefore since an אשם asham is male and an עולה ola
is male, so this in theory could be used as an עולה.
ola. So once it's been put on that path and given out
to pasture, okay, at that stage if you שחט'ד shechted it סתם,
stam, it would function as an עולה. ola. Now, why is that
relevant? Because the point here is ניתק אין לא ניתק לא. nitak
in lo nitak lo. It's only when it's been like removed from
its old state and put out to pasture that now we say
if you שחט, shecht, you're not supposed to שחט shecht it at
this stage. You're supposed to wait for it to be a blemish
and redeem it etc. But if you did שחט shecht it, we
say it would now be an עולה. ola. Okay, but that's only
once something has done to put it on a different path. Now
that it's been put out to pasture. If after the אשם asham
couldn't be brought because the owner brought let's say another one or
whatever, you haven't put it out to pasture yet and you שחט'ד
shechted it, it would be invalid. So where do we get this
idea? Either way eventually it's going to be used for an עולה.
ola. Where do we get the idea that you have to do
something with it, put it out to pasture to somewhat uproot its
previous identity and now make it that it would be valid as
an עולה? ola? So that you know the גמרא Gemara says אמר
קרא הוא בהוייתו יהא. amar kra hu bhavyaso yehei. That we learn
from the word הוא. hu. אשם הוא. asham hu. אשם הוא asham
hu means that its identity is like a sticky identity. Okay, it
remains in its status. So here's this אשם, asham, can no longer
be brought because the owner's brought let's say another one, okay, and
it eventually it's going to be turning into an עולה, ola, but
because of the idea of הוא hu which gives it this like
sticky identity, it if you שחט shecht it now it will be
invalid. valid. You have to do something active and concrete to change
its identity. You have to put it out to pasture. And at
that stage, because then it removes from that הוא hu status, from
that sticky identity, and at that stage if you שחט shechted it,
it would be treated as an עולה. olah. Okay. So that's what
you learn from the word הוא hu by an אשם, asham, but
general the word היא hi by a חטאת chatas and a מנחת
חוטא minchas chotei and מנחת קנאות minchas kenaos because they appear earlier
in the פסוקים, pesukim, that earlier in the process, that teaches you
that שלא לשמו shelo lishmo is invalid. All right? So that's the
הלכה halacha of שלא לשמו. shelo lishmo. Now we move on. אמר
רב, Amar Rav, says Rav. Now we're going to sort of add
to the list in the משנה Mishna about types of מנחות minchos
that can be fully invalid. Okay. אמר רב, Amar Rav, says Rav:
מנחת העומר שקמצה שלא לשמו. Minchas ha'omer shekimtza shelo lishmo. You did
the קמיצה kemitza of שלא לשמו shelo lishmo by a מנחת העומר,
minchas ha'omer, מנחה mincha coming on, you know, the second day of
פסח Pesach to make the new grain permissible. So he says, פסולה,
pesula, that's invalid, although our משנה Mishna only mentioned two: a מנחת
חוטא minchas chotei and a מנחת קנאות. minchas kenaos. He says this
also would be invalid. Why would it be invalid? הואיל ובאה להתיר
ולא התירה. Ho'il uvasa lehatir velo hetira. Okay. He does it totally
by logic. He says look, this has one function. The function of
this is to make the new grain permissible. Now once you do
it שלא לשמו, shelo lishmo, now we've never actually said this, we
said that שלא לשמו shelo lishmo means the owners don't get credit,
right? You could imagine if I did a מנחת העומר minchas ha'omer
שלא לשמו, shelo lishmo, the owners don't get credit, I mean nobody
needs credit here anyway, and maybe it still does its old function,
maybe it's still a מנחת העומר minchas ha'omer and the same way
the הלכה halacha would be that you could eat the remainder of
it because it's not intrinsically invalid, maybe it could do its function,
maybe it could still allow the new grain to be eaten, right?
Who said not? But he is assuming since it no longer connects
to the owners, if it was my private מנחה mincha and I
brought it and it was שלא לשמו, shelo lishmo, once it's שלא
לשמו shelo lishmo it no longer connects to me, it's just like
an עומר omer living in a vacuum, so the same would be
true when the ציבור tzibur brings a מנחת העומר. minchas ha'omer. Once
it's שלא לשמו shelo lishmo it detaches itself from the ציבור, tzibur,
it's just a living in a vacuum, if it's living in a
vacuum and it's not connected to the ציבור tzibur whatever, then it
doesn't have this identity of מנחת העומר minchas ha'omer anymore and it
can't be מתיר matir the new grain. Okay, so that's assumption number
one. Now at the same way שלא לשמו shelo lishmo means the
owners don't get credit, שלא לשמו shelo lishmo means it doesn't have
its sort of its meaningful identity and it can't מתיר matir the
new grain. Now that's assumption, now assertion or assumption number two is
that if it's not doing its function, it's completely worthless and invalid
and therefore it's not a good קרבן korban and it's פסול pasul
and you can't eat the remainder. Now the obvious question is: wait,
why is that different than other things that don't do their function?
Meaning a normal מנחה mincha שלא לשמו shelo lishmo you could say
it's not about a function, it's just about an offering to God.
So if the owners aren't getting credit or whatever, it's still it's
still an offering, you still put it on the מזבח, mizbeach, it's
something put on the מזבח mizbeach to God. But there are things
that serve a particular function other than מנחת העומר. minchas ha'omer. What
type of a קרבן korban serves a particular function? David, what would
you say? You didn't hear the question. Okay. So it's alright. What
type of קרבן korban serves a function? Meaning is not just an
offering to God, but does something, the same way a מנחת העומר
minchas ha'omer allows the new grain to be eaten? Maybe like a
נזיר nazir or something? Well, okay, the נזיר nazir we're going to
get to but, yes, but the more obvious thing to say I
would say is a sin offering. A sin offering's purpose is to
achieve atonement, right? Or an אשם. asham. Alright, an אשם's asham purpose
is to achieve atonement. So if you say a מנחת העומר, minchas
ha'omer, if it doesn't do its job, if it doesn't מתיר matir
the new grain it's totally invalid. So if an אשם's asham whole
job is to atone, if it doesn't atone because it's שלא לשמו,
shelo lishmo, why don't we also say it's invalid? Okay, so he's
introducing this new idea: something that's got a job to do, if
it's not doing its job the whole thing is invalid. And so
therefore שלא לשמו shelo lishmo means it's not doing its job, so
therefore the whole thing is invalid. So that's what he says by
a מנחת העומר, minchas ha'omer, but the obvious question that the גמרא's
Gemara going to ask is that then you should say it by
an אשם asham as well. Okay, things that- now by a חטאת
chatas we do say it's invalid. Okay, but if you're making a
general principle that if it's not doing its job it should be
invalid, okay,
why just limit it to this? So let's take a look where
this goes. Is there a distinction between the communal and the private?
So could be that- that could be. He doesn't say that, but
that's a good thought. The thought would be maybe this is just
a הלכה halacha about a communal קרבן, korban, maybe a private קרבן
korban somehow goes by different rules. The גמרא Gemara doesn't give that
answer, but that's a good thought. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says:
וכן אתה אומר באשם נזיר, Vechain ata omer be'asham nazir,
now he himself does compare to certain types of אשמות. ashamos. Okay,
an אשם נזיר asham nazir and an אשם מצורע. asham metzora. Now
what's the story about an אשם נזיר asham nazir and an אשם
מצורע? asham metzora? So an אשם asham who becomes טמא- tamei an
אשם- asham a נזיר nazir who becomes טמא, tamei, he brings an
in order to start his נזירות nezirut again. And a מצורע metzora
brings an אשם asham in order to become טהור, tahor, become part
of the טהרה tahara process. Now a lot of people bring a
חטאת chatat as part of the טהרה tahara process, but that's obvious.
We know a חטאת שלא לשמה chatat shelo lishmo is invalid. He's
coming to expand the things that are invalid. So he's saying I'll
even give you an אשם asham that's invalid. An אשם asham of
a נזיר nazir and an אשם asham of a מצורע, metzora, their
job is להכשיר, l'hachshir, their job is basically to change status, the
same way the job of a מנחת העומר minchat ha'omer was to
change the status of a grain. And his principle is, any קרבן
korban that's coming to change status, and here David you see even
a private קרבן, korban, once it's not doing its job, once it's
שלא לשמה shelo lishmo it can't do its job, and once it's
not doing its job, the whole thing is invalid. So that's really
broadening the scope of שלא לשמה shelo lishmo that's invalid. But as
I said, then the question should be every אשם asham is coming
to do a job. If it's not coming for טהרה tahara purposes,
it's coming for כפרה kapara purposes. So what's the difference? So the
גמרא Gemara is going to ask that. שלא לשמן פסולין הואיל ובאו
להכשיר ולא הכשירו. shelo lishmam psulin ho'il u'va'u l'hachshir v'lo hichshiru. Now
before it gets to that question, which is the foremost in my
mind, the גמרא Gemara is going to say wait, how does this
fit in to all of our משניות? mishnayot? Until now we've went
through all the זבחים zvachim in the beginning of מנחות, Menachot, and
we said which שלא לשמה's shelo lishmo are invalid, and we never
said these cases. We never said מנחת העומר minchat ha'omer in any
משנה, mishnah, we never said an אשם מצורע asham metzora or an
אשם נזיר. asham nazir. How can you all of a sudden say
that שלא לשמה shelo lishmo invalidates here? So the גמרא Gemara says
let's take a look. That's going to be the textual test. תנן,
tnan, our משנה mishnah says:
כל המנחות שנקמצו שלא לשמן כשרות אלא שלא עלו לבעלים לשם חובה.
kol hamenachot shenikmetzu shelo lishmam ksherot ela shelo alu l'va'alim l'shem chova.
They're כשרות ksherot but the owners don't get credit, חוץ ממנחת חוטא
ומנחת קנאות, chutz mi'minchat chote u'minchat kna'ot, except for the מנחה mincha
of the sinner and the מנחה mincha of a סוטה. sota. ואם
איתא, v'im ita, if what you're saying is true, that it's also
מנחת העומר, minchat ha'omer, ליתני נמי חוץ ממנחת העומר, litni nami chutz
mi'minchat ha'omer, then it should have said מנחת העומר minchat ha'omer שלא
לשמה shelo lishmo invalidates. So the גמרא Gemara says no, כי קתני
ביחיד בצבור לא קתני. ki katani b'yachid, b'tzibur lo katani. So David,
this is similar to your point, but this is a textual answer.
It's not about his principle. His rule applies to private and public
קרבנות, korbanot, like we see by the אשם. asham. But why the
משנה mishnah didn't mention the exception of מנחת העומר minchat ha'omer is
the משנה mishnah is dealing with private קרבנות, korbanot, so it didn't
mention the exception of מנחת העומר minchat ha'omer because it's not dealing
with public
קרבנות. korbanot. כי קתני, ki katani, and another explanation, באה בגלל עצמה
באה בגלל זבח לא קתני. ba'a biglal atzma, ba'a biglal zevach lo
katani. The משנה mishnah is talking about a מנחה mincha that comes
on its own. מנחת העומר minchat ha'omer comes with an animal קרבן.
korban. So you're right, it should have mentioned מנחת העומר minchat ha'omer
as an exception, but it wasn't dealing with those cases. It was
dealing with private קרבנות, korbanot, it was dealing with מנחות minchot that
come on their own, and another answer, כי קתני הנהך שאין קבוע
להן זמן הקבוע להן זמן לא קתני. ki katani hanach she'ein kavua
lahen zman, hakavua lahen zman lo katani. It's talking about מנחות minchot
that come at any time. A מנחת העומר minchat ha'omer comes at
a regular fixed
time, it's related to the
מועד mo'ed cycle. You're right, it really is an exception and the
משנה mishnah in theory should have listed it, but the משנה mishnah
isn't dealing with those types of cases so it didn't bother to
mention it. All right, now we're going to have to ask about
the exception about the אשם נזיר asham nazir and אשם מצורע, asham
metzora, because guess what? That wasn't mentioned in our משנה mishnah way
back in זבחים Zvachim either. אמר מר, amar mar, so let's go
back to the statement: וכן אתה אומר באשם נזיר ובאשם מצורע ששחטן
שלא לשמן פסולין הואיל ובאו להכשיר ולא הכשירו. v'chen ata omer b'asham
nazir u'v'asham metzora sheshachtan shelo lishmam psulin ho'il u'va'u l'hachshir v'lo hichshiru.
All right, so let's first ask the textual question. תנן, tnan, we
have the first משנה mishnah in
זבחים, Zvachim, כל הזבחים ששחטן שלא לשמן כשרים אלא שלא עלו לבעלים
לשם חובה. kol hazvachim sheshachtan shelo lishmam ksherim ela shelo alu l'va'alim
l'shem chova. So they're כשרים ksherim but the owners don't get credit,
חוץ מפסח וחטאת, chutz mi'pesach v'chatat, except for פסח pesach and חטאת.
chatat. ואם איתא, v'im ita, if what you're saying is correct, that
an אשם נזיר asham nazir and אשם מצורע asham metzora is also
invalid, ליתני נמי חוץ מאשם נזיר ואשם מצורע. litni nami chutz mi'asham
nazir v'asham metzora. Why not mention those in that first משנה mishnah
in זבחים? Zvachim? So the גמרא Gemara says דבאו להכשיר ולא הכשירו,
d'ba'u l'hachshir v'lo hichshiru, they're coming to change the status and they
didn't. And you can't give all the answers we gave because those
are not public, those are private, those come on their own, and
those don't come at a fixed time. So you got a real
question, that should have been mentioned over in that משנה mishnah in
זבחים Zvachim that those things are also an exception. So the גמרא
Gemara says no, כיון דאיכא אשם גזלות ואשם מעילות דלכפרה אתו לא
פסיקא ליה. kivan d'ika asham gezelot v'asham meilot d'l'chapara atu lo psika
lei. The גמרא Gemara says no, because we're talking about whole categories.
So since there are some אשמות ashamot that are valid, like an
אשם asham that's about sin, that is valid if it's שלא לשמה,
shelo lishmo, that's if he's stealing things or מעילה. meila. So therefore
we didn't, what it's excluding there is genres of קרבן. korban. It
says a חטאת chatat שלא לשמה shelo lishmo is invalid, a פסח
pesach שלא לשמה shelo lishmo is invalid. By an אשם asham we
would have had to get into subdividing the category, and we would
have had to say some אשמות ashamot שלא לשמה shelo lishmo are
invalid, the ones that are about status, נזיר nazir and מצורע, metzora,
others, the ones that are about sin, שלא לשמה shelo lishmo is
valid. So we didn't mention it because we didn't want to get
into subdividing the category. dividing a category. We only wanted to talk
about whole categories that are exceptions. So חטאת Chatas and a פסח
Pesach are an entire category that's an exception, אשם, Asham, some are
an exception and some are not. Okay. So now we're done with
the textual issue. Now we have to get to the conceptual question,
which is why should an אשם Asham of status more be said
it didn't do its job and it's פסול, passul, and an אשם
Asham about sin could be כשר kosher even if it's not doing
its job? So that we still have to ask. Yes, so that's
exactly the point I've been saying and that finally now the גמרא'ס
Gemara's going to get to ask. Okay. And this is sin, but
חטאת Chatas is sin. Yeah, and you would until now—right, until now,
everything about חטאת Chatas has all been since it can't function anymore
in terms of atoning for the sin, it's invalid. Right. Now, of
course, אשם Asham is the exception. We've known אשם Asham is the
exception because from the very beginning of זבחים Zevachim we know that
even though an אשם Asham can't atone for a sin, you know,
at this stage, right, you know, because it's שלא לשמה, shelo lishma,
nevertheless somehow it's still it's not like a חטאת, Chatas, it's allowed
to be brought up. Okay. But then, but then how do you
say that it's more important that when it can't do a function
like change a status, that more invalidates it than when it can't
do a function like atone for sin? So that's what the גמרא
Gemara is going to ask. See how it's brought up, it's not
fulfilling the owner's obligation. Right. It's just to me. Exactly. Exactly. So
then the question is why that function, when it can't do it,
it's still valid, whereas when it can't do the function of changing
status, it's invalid. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay.
מאי שנא אשם נזיר ואשם מצורע דבאו להכשיר ולא הכשירו? Mai shna
Asham Nazir ve'Asham Metzora de'ba'u lehachshir velo hichshiru?
So because those are coming to change status and they're not doing
it, they're invalid. הני נמי באו לכפר ולא כיפר? Hani nami ba'u
lechaper velo kiper? So by these other אשמות, Ashamos, they're coming to
atone and they didn't atone, so by your logic, if it's not
doing its function, those should be invalid. Okay,
אמר רב ירמיה—excellent Amar Rav Yirmiya question—so the גמרא, Gemara, rather than
giving a sort of like
a—shows that this distinction is relevant without explaining why. אמר רב ירמיה
מצינו שחילק הכתוב בין מכפרים ובין מכשירים. Amar Rav Yirmiya matzinu she'chilek
ha'katuv bein mechaperim uvein machshirin.
We find that the תורה Torah sometimes like makes a difference. That
when something is coming for a status change, we don't do it
when the status change is no longer relevant. Whereas when something is
coming for atonement, we do it when the atonement is no longer
relevant. What is this case? Show me where this is. Okay. מכפרים
אית בהו דאתו לאחר מיתה. Mechaperim is be'hu de'asu le'achar misa.
There are cases after somebody dies, you'll bring something that's for their
atonement. Now, that's not a standard case. A normal person dies and
they have a חטאת, Chatas, you don't bring the חטאת Chatas for
the person after they died. A normal person dies and they have
an אשם, Asham, you don't bring the אשם. Asham. I mean, you
might transfer the אשם Asham to an עולה, Olah, but you don't
bring it as an אשם. Asham. So the general rule is you
don't bring something that is sin-related after somebody dies. But he says,
I'm going to show you something, there are some cases we do
that, that there's an idea of sin-related after, atonement-related after dies, ומכשירים
לית בהו לאחר מיתה, u'machshirin leis be'hu le'achar misa, and you never
find something that is about changing of a status that's brought after
somebody dies. What's the case? Okay. דתנן, De'isnan, we learned in the
משנה, Mishnah, האישה שהביאה חטאתה
ומתה. ha'ishah she'hevia chatasah u'mesa. Now a woman gave birth—had a
baby. And after she had a baby, she's obligated to bring a
קרבן korban for childbirth, a חטאת Chatas and an עולה. Olah. Okay.
Now she goes ahead and she brought her חטאת Chatas and then
she died. So יביאו יורשים עולתה, yaviu yorshim olasa, so the heirs
bring her עולה. Olah. Fine, that's just an עולה, Olah, that's not
כפרה kaparah related, that's an עולה. Olah. Okay. עולתה ומתה לא יביאו
יורשים חטאתה. olasah u'mesa lo yaviu yorshim chatasah. She brought her עולה
Olah and she died,
don't bring the חטאת. Chatas. Now, the fact that you don't bring
the חטאת, Chatas, fine, that's the general rule. Somebody is dead, you
don't bring something that is a חטאת. Chatas. But here, what's he
getting at of all of this? So what he's getting out of
all of this is something that's not so obvious, but what he's
getting about this is is that the חטאת Chatas of a יולדת,
yoledes, because a יולדת yoledes is not really sin-related, okay, so the
חטאת Chatas of a יולדת yoledes is not coming לכפרה. le'kaparah. The
חטאת Chatas of a יולדת yoledes is coming to allow her to
get out of her טומאה tumah status and allow her to eat
קרבנות. korbanos. So the חטאת Chatas is להכשיר, lehachshir, okay? So you've
got your יולדת yoledes and she has two things: an עולה Olah
and a חטאת. Chatas. This חטאת Chatas is להכשיר. lehachshir. Fine. And
you're not going to bring it after she dies. You don't bring
something that's להכשיר lehachshir after somebody dies. What does that tell you
about the עולה? Olah? So for some reason we're assuming that the
עולה Olah is לכפר. lechaper.
Why we're assuming that is strange, why does she even need כפרה?
kaparah? Okay. So רש"י Rashi says, אחד לחטאת ואחד לעולה. echad le'chatas
ve'echad le'olah. So somehow we learn, I don't know why, like we're
assuming if one is להכשיר, lehachshir, the other is לכפר. lechaper. Okay.
So if we bring this—we don't bring this after she dies—so that's
the rule, you don't bring something that's coming, you don't bring a
חטאת Chatas anyway after she dies. We don't bring something that's coming
to change a status. This you bring after she dies and we're
going to assert, you could have just said that's because it's an
עולה, olah, it's not coming to do anything, but we're going to
assert that her עולה olah is coming לכפר lechaper and you do
bring it after she dies. So his assertion is ah, so therefore
there are times if something isn't a חטאת chatas where something could
be sin-related and brought after somebody is dead. So there is a
possible thing of a קרבן korban that's identity is about sin or
sin-related or כפרה-related kapparah that still is brought even when it's not
doing its function. So he says that's what you have by a
יולדת yoledes when you bring her עולה olah after she's dead. It's
not doing its function. Its function was לכפר. lechaper. It's too late
לכפר, lechaper, the person is dead. Okay, but nevertheless you bring it
and that would be an אשם שלא לשמו. asham shelo lishmo. An
אשם שלא לשמו, asham shelo lishmo, yes it's coming לכפר, lechaper, but
things which are coming about atonement can be brought even when they're
not doing their function. But things that are coming just to change
status are only being brought when they're doing their function, okay? Which
is
conceptually the way I would say it is and I'm not sure
this is exactly what the גמרא's Gemara getting at but I would
sort of say that if something is coming לכפר, lechaper,
basically it's being brought to God, right? And therefore even if it's
not achieving its goal of כפרה, kapparah, its identity still is like
an offering to God, right? Whereas something that is coming like להכשיר
lehachshir to change and get out of a טומאה tumah status or
whatever, it might be seen more as like a ritual, its emphasis
more is getting the function done and as a ritual to change
status than it is as an offering to God. And therefore if
it's not having that function, it doesn't have any more of an
identity left. Why why should you bring it? This whole thing was
just about moving on to the next stage. It wasn't about some
intrinsic sense of an offering. Where something that's coming לכפר, lechaper, the
כפרה kapparah is achieved through it being an offering. But it starts
with the idea of it being something offered to God. And therefore
maybe even if it can't do that function of כפרה, kapparah, this
אשם asham it could still be the offering. So that's how a
little bit how I would see it that something coming לכפר lechaper
is fundamentally an offering that achieves כפרה, kapparah, whereas something that is
coming להכשיר lehachshir to change a status is fundamentally like some the
same way for example it works less by עומר, omer, works better
by the טומאה. tumah. The same way you can change טומאה tumah
statuses in other ways. You change the טומאה tumah status by going
to the מקוה. mikveh. You change a טומאה tumah status by sprinkling
the ashes of a פרה אדומה. parah adumah. So sometimes you change
a טומאה tumah status by bringing a קרבן, korban, but it's a
type of a just ritual and a function of changing status. It's
not so much of an offering as its identity. So once it's
not changing status, there's nothing left and it can't be brought, okay?
Where something that fundamentally is an offering that just achieves כפרה, kapparah,
even if it's not achieving כפרה kapparah can still be brought. That's
the way I'd like to see it although by עומר, omer, עומר
omer you would still think is fundamentally about an offering so I
don't totally get the distinction. What do you want to ask? Okay,
alright so that's basically the difference that something whose job is only
for changing status if it can't do the function is פסול. pasul.
מנחת עומר, minchas omer, אשם נזיר, asham nazir, אשם מצורע. asham metzora.
Something whose job is to achieve atonement well if it's a חטאת,
chatas, that's just a הלכה. halacha. חטאת שלא לשמו chatas shelo lishmo
is invalid. But if you have something that's כפרה-related kapparah that's not
a חטאת, chatas, i.e. an אשם, asham, that actually can continue to
be brought even when it can't do its function. Okay so now
the גמרא Gemara says like
this. Where were we? מסקיף לה רב יהודה בריה דרב שמעון בן
פזי. maskif lah Rav Yehuda birei de-Rav Shimon ben Pazi. So רב
יהודה Rav Yehuda challenges. מכשיר נמי מי איתיה לאחר מיתה? machshir nami
mi isyei le-achar misa? I'll show you something that's a מכשיר, machshir,
that's a status change, that also exists when it's not doing its
function. It also exists לאחר מיתה. le-achar misa. How do you have
that? Here's the הלכה. halacha. דתנן detnan we learned in a משנה.
Mishnah. המפריש מעות לנזירותו. hamafrish ma'os li-neziruso. Somebody is a נזיר nazir
and sets aside money for their קרבנות. korbanos. Now a נזיר nazir
has to bring three קרבנות. korbanos. Okay, a חטאת, chatas, an עולה,
olah, and a שלמים shelamim at the end of their נזירות. nezirus.
So they set aside a pile of money for these three קרבנות.
korbanos.
Now לא נהנין ולא מועלין. lo nehenin velo mo'alin. Now if somebody
went ahead and used all of that money for going out and
buying to the supermarket you would not even though you're not allowed
to you would not transgress מעילה. me'ilah. Why not? It's money for
a חטאת, chatas, it's money for an עולה. olah. Because מפני שראויין
לבא כולן שלמים. mipnei she-re'uyin lavo kullan shelamim. Since he didn't designate
how those funds would be distributed, it could be that he could
use all those funds to buy a שלמים shelamim and he'd buy
the חטאת chatas and עולה olah from different monies. And therefore there's
no מעילה me'ilah by a שלמים. shelamim. Since the owners eat the
שלמים, shelamim, there's only מעילה me'ilah after it's been brought and then
only by the אימורים, imurim, only by the entrails. So therefore since
we don't know its identity has not been solidified and it's potentially
all just a שלמים, shelamim, there's no מעילה. me'ilah. Okay.
now let's say he died. והיו לו מעות סתומים, Vehayu lo maos
stumim, and this money was not designated. Is it חטאת, chatas, is
it עולה, olah, is it שלמים? shelamim? You know, he had this
pile of money for his נזיר. nazir. So the הלכה halacha is
יפלו לנדבה. yipplu l'nedava. All of that money gets put into the
box and used for these communal עולות. olos. That's just like a
הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha l'moshe mi-sinai. That's what you do with the
money if it's not designated and he dies.
מפורשים, Meforashim, now let's say he said, he said, "this money I'm
going to bring a חטאת, chatas, this I'm going to bring an
עולה, olah, this I'm going to bring a שלמים." shelamim. He had
these three piles and then he dropped dead. What do you do
with the moneys that were for these various קרבנות? korbanos? Okay, so
דמי חטאת ילכו לים המלח. dmei chatas yelechu l'yam hamelach.
The money for a חטאת, chatas, the same way if it was
an animal חטאת chatas and the owner died, we say the חטאת
chatas would have to die, right? That's the הלכה, halacha, right? חטאת
המיתות. chatas hamisos. So the money has the same הלכה, halacha, it
has to get destroyed and you throw it out. לא נהנין ולא
מועלין. lo nehenin v'lo moalin. But there's no, you're not allowed to
derive personal benefit but there's no מעילה. meilah. Since it's no longer
going to God, since it's going to get thrown out, there's no
מעילה. meilah.
דמי עולה, Dmei olah, the money of an עולה, olah, יביא בהן
עולה. yavi bahen olah. So that you use for an עולה, olah,
because why not? The guy's dead, fine, but we can still bring
an עולה. olah. ומועלין בהן, um-moalin bahen, and the איסור מעילה issur
meilah applies. דמי שלמים, Dmei shelamim, יביא בהן שלמים, yavi bahen shelamim,
and the שלמים shelamim money you use for
שלמים. shelamim. ונאכלין ליום אחד, v'ne'echalin l'yom echad, and they're eaten for
one day, which is like the שלמים shelamim of a נזיר nazir
as opposed to a normal שלמים shelamim that you eat in two
days. ואינן טעונין לחם, ve'einan te'unim lechem, but you don't bring the
bread that you bring with a שלמים shelamim of a נזיר, nazir,
because that requires an actually, to be brought by a נזיר nazir
to have the bread. Okay. Now, how is this relevant? Because the
guy's dead and you're bringing his עולה olah and his שלמים. shelamim.
Now, his עולה olah and שלמים shelamim were part of the process
of the קרבנות korbanot that were going to change his status. So
you see you can bring a קרבן korban that is coming to
change status even if the owner is dead. So you can have
a status change קרבן korban without it actually doing its job. And
if that's true there should also be true by your cases, the
אשם נזיר asham nazir and so on. So the גמרא Gemara says,
והא עולה ושלמים דנזיר דמכשירין נינהו? ve'ha olah u-shelamim de'nazir de-machshirin ninhu?
Those are about status change. And by the way, the reason it's
different than the אשם נזיר asham nazir is the אשם נזיר asham
nazir was a נזיר nazir who was טמא. tamei. So for נזיר
טמא nazir tamei to start again the טהרה tahara process, not to
end his נזירות, nezirus, but to begin the נזירות nezirus of טהרה,
tahara, that's the אשם נזיר asham nazir we were talking about. This
is the נזיר nazir who ends his process of טהרה tahara and
he's really done, done, and for him he brings a חטאת chatas
and an עולה olah and a שלמים. shelamim. But it's very parallel.
It's the קרבנות korbanot brought by a נזיר nazir at the end
of one period to begin the next or change the status. So
if by an אשם asham of a נזיר nazir you say it
can't be brought when it's not functioning, why can you bring the
עולה olah and the שלמים shelamim when they're not doing their function?
Okay, דקאתו אחר מיתה. de-ka'asu achar misah. So that's the question. So
אמר רב פפא amar Rav Pappa says רב פפא, Rav Pappa, הכי
קאמר רבי ירמיה, hachi ka'amar Rabbi Yirmiyah, this is what רבי ירמיה
Rabbi Yirmiyah says, הכי קאמר רבי ירמיה, hachi ka'amar Rabbi Yirmiyah, this
is what רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiyah meant to say. לא מצינו הכשר
קבוע דבא אחר מיתה. lo matzinu hechsher kavua de-ba achar misah. All
of רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiyah's cases, the אשם asham of the נזיר
nazir and the מצורע metzora and the מנחת העומר, minchas ha-omer, that
is the only thing that is doing the change of status. The
entire change of status rests on that thing. So its entire identity
is about changing status. And when it can't do that, it's invalid.
But by the נזיר, nazir, by the עולה olah and the שלמים
shelamim of a נזיר, nazir, והנזיר הכשר שאינו קבוע הוא. ve'hanazir hechsher
she-eino kavua hu. The עולה olah and the שלמים shelamim don't have
to be the ones that are changing the status. There are three
קרבנות korbanot and any one of them can change the status. Okay,
דאמר מר, de-amar mar, גילח על אחת משלש יצא. gile'ach al achas
mishalosh yatza. Even if you just brought one of the קרבנות, korbanot,
just the חטאת, chatas, just the עולה, olah, just the שלמים, shelamim,
he's allowed to do the shaving or whatever and his status changes.
He's obligated in the other קרבנות, korbanot, but there's not any, no
one of them in particular is needed. Any one of them can
change the status. So that actually is a very good answer, right?
If something, it's the only thing that changes the status, that's its
identity, and if it can't change status, it's invalid. That's the אשם
asham of a נזיר, nazir, the אשם asham of a מצורע, metzora,
the מנחת עומר. minchas omer. But here where he brings three קרבנות,
korbanot, even though this one could be about status change, it doesn't
have to be. The other one could be about status change. So
since its entire identity is not status change, that function could be
taken up by any of the other one, any of the other
קרבנות, korbanot, it's valid even when it's no longer able to function
להכשיר le'hachshir because that never had to be its identity anyway. It
was always able to function independent of
that
regardless. Okay, so we will continue with this discussion tomorrow.